So our game is slowly developing, and in the previous lesson we looked at how kicking could take place
with the goalie turtle and the ball turtle, and how we could adjust the angle so that it was random
so it would make it a little bit more exciting.
And so the goalie could go up and down in that sort of position and try and save those balls.
But now what we need to do is we need to obviously have a function that allows us to to move the goalie
up and down.
And so essentially we're going to need two functions because we're going to need a function that's going
to move the goalie up.
And then we're going to need another function that's going to move the goalie down.
And that's going to be responding to the up and down arrows on our keyboard.
And then also ultimately we're also going to want to call our kick function as well.
So we'll have a look at that in this lesson on how to create those functions.
So our first function we need to define in order to teach our goalie how to save is this goalie app
function.
So again it's just a simple diff.
And we've called our function goalie app.
So in order to get our goalie to go up we want it to face north which was this nine degree angle.
So I've set the goalie to go north, and I want the goalie to just move forward by five pixels, which
is pretty small.
But you'll understand why when I get to this part down here.
So for now, goalie up.
All it does is it points out turtle to go upwards and it moves it forward by five.
Then this function over here is pretty much the opposite of the goalie up.
It's making the goalie go down.
So what we're doing is we are setting the heading or setting the direction of the goalie downwards or
south, which is 270 degrees.
And we are again moving the goalie forward by five.
But this forward now will be going downwards.
You're going to be a very good Boy scout or girl guard or whatever it is after this, but you should
know all your directions.
Okay?
But now none of this really does anything without the function ever being called.
So like we said earlier, this function didn't actually do anything because we never called it the way
we want to call these functions in our game is actually a special way or a way we have not done before.
What we want to do is we want the screen to wait for a key to be pressed.
So the screen variable has this method called on key press.
And what basically happens here, the screen variable over here which we defined at the top which is
a turtle screen has a function that we can use on it called on key press.
Now what this function does for us is it takes two parameters.
And that is a function as the first parameter and a key on our keyboard as a second parameter.
And what it does is it takes whatever function you want and it binds it to a key on the keyboard.
For example, here we have taken the up key and we've told it whenever the up key is pressed call call
this function called go up.
So every time I click the up key when our game is running, it is going to call this function and do
what is inside.
So basically change it to north and move it forward five spaces.
So that's why I only had to move it forward by five because instead of moving it a huge distance, I
rather want to make it.
If the key is being pressed, then keep on moving it up those five spaces.
We then have again the same thing, but obviously this is just doing go down with the down key.
So the down key calls this function go down.
And then for the kicking because we want the ball obviously to move forward and be kicked.
I've chosen just to use the k key on the keyboard.
So I mean you can make it anything.
You can make it the J, you can make it the L whatever you want.
But we've told it when key is pressed, call the kick function.
Now if you have these on key press and key methods where you are using the keyboard and you want the
program to wait for a key to be pressed, then we need this other function down here called screen Dot.
Listen.
And basically what this does is it just the program will constantly wait for a key to be pressed.
And if a key is pressed then it realizes it and it will run this function.
So without this, our program is not going to bother listening for any keys and it will most likely
crash.
And then another thing you should always have is your in your program.
Is this line over here.
And this line is basically just always in the last line of your program, and it needs it for it to
run.
I'm pressing the K keyboard now on the screen.
And as you can see our ball has moved forward.
So I missed it that time.
Uh, and then our other thing that we defined in our program was obviously moving the turtle up and
down.
So if I click the down key, it does that.
If I click the up key it is going to do that.
So basically all we have is we can kick with the K and we can move the turtle up and down to try and
save the ball with the up and down keys.
So you can keep on doing this as many times as you would like.
This looks like a fun game.
This is going to be a best seller, definitely.
I'm sure you will all make a whole lot of money with this game.
But yeah, and once you're done, you click exit.
And yeah, we've got the beginnings of a game working.
All that's really left to do now is make it look a little bit pretty, add a field and doing that we'll
show you how to use loops in it and all kinds of exciting things.